Guide to the Marjorie Rice Daltry Rosenbaum Papers, 1968 - 2012
Marjorie Rice Daltry Rosenbaum Papers1968 - 2012
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Marjorie Rice Daltry Rosenbaum
2013-20
3.9
8
Marjorie Rice Daltry Rosenbaum (May 10, 1921-October 20, 2013) was a dedicated woman who sought to make the experience of public and private school education better. Her programs, including the major C.A.U.S.E. Program that started in 1967, created a cooperative framework for Wesleyan to interact and learn from the Middletown community. She was a life long Connecticut resident who both went to and taught in many of the public schools as an English, social studies, and choral music teacher and later became chief administrator of Wesleyan's Educational Studies Program from 1973-1985.
The Marjorie Rice Daltry Rosenbaum Papers contain both work and personal papers relating to her educational programs and life. The majority of the papers in the collection relate to C.A.U.S.E. and its corresponding programs, but there are documents that relate to other programs that she was involved with during her life. The work papers in the collection are made up of photos, newspaper articles and general press, meeting minutes, proposals, evaluations, and correspondence with principals or directors of certain schools and programs. The personal papers include personal correspondence, drawings, resumes and vitaes, and papers corresponding to specific individuals. The correspondence for the programs generally concerns how the program is fairing or requesting certain aid or resources. The personal correspondence ranges from the familial to more business oriented topics.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Gift of Marjorie Rice Daltry Rosenbaum.
Biographical Note
Marjorie Suzanne Rice Daltry Rosenbaum was born on May 10, 1921 in Hartford, CT to Louis Haskell Rice and Guilelma Murray Rice, and was the older sister of Charles Murray Rice. She was a resident of Connecticut her entire life, and lived in West Hartford until relocating to Middletown in the 1950s. She attended school within the West Hartford public school system until her graduation from Hall High School. In 1943, she graduated with a BA from Radcliffe College in Cambridge, MA, with a major in English and a minor in music.
After graduating from college, she returned to West Hartford and took up a teaching position at Sedgwick Junior High School. She remained there until 1957 as the chairman of the English department and as an instructor of both choral music and social studies. While at Sedgwick, she also completed a Master of Arts in Liberal Studies (MALS) in music, theatre, and art in 1955 at Wesleyan University. In doing so, Marjorie became one of the original graduates of Wesleyan's Graduate Liberal Studies Program (GLSP). During her life, Marjorie also completed additional graduate work at Harvard University, the University of Connecticut, and Central Connecticut State College.
Between 1957 and 1973, Marjorie continued to teach in the West Hartford, Haddam, and Middletown public schools until she retired in June 1973 after 30 years of service. She also performed in and directed a number of concerts and musicals in both a professional and recreational capacity. A number of these productions were in Wesleyan's student run '92 Theatre or for the Theatre Department including The Tempest, a Cole Porter concert, and a number of cabarets. She also made the Broadway cast of Kiss Me Kate, which came to Broadway in 1948.
In 1956, she married Joseph S. Daltry, founder, chairman, and first instructor of the Music Deparment at Wesleyan University and director of the MALS program. The two remained together until Joseph S. Daltry's death in 1967 at age 68.
She did not just dedicate her life to teaching within an establsihed system, but sought to create a new and better educational experience for students within the public school system. To this end, she founded C.A.U.S.E. (Community And University Services for Education) in 1967. C.A.U.S.E. was set up as a cooperative program meant to facilitate projects between Wesleyan University and the Middletown community and public and private schools in the area. She felt that a university, any university, owed something to the community it was in. By 1980, C.A.U.S.E. had either been involved in or supported over 45 distinct programs to support the schools in the Middletown area. These projects ranged from breakfast programs, to enrichment summer school, to art and dance programs, and adult education. She remained C.A.U.S.E.'s principal strength throughout her life. She later became chief administrator of Wesleyan's Educational Studies Program from 1973-1985.
She remarried Wesleyan Professor Emeritus of Science and Mathematics Robert A. Rosenbaum and remained with him until her death on October 20, 2013 in Delta, Colorado. Marjorie was a woman who always gave back and always sought to make the experience of others as beneficial and exciting as possible. As her obituary in the Hartford Courant wrote, "She was a woman of cultured substance, demonstrative presence, and memorable performance."
Collection Overview
The Marjorie Rice Daltry Rosenbaum Papers contain both work and personal papers relating to her educational programs and life. The majority of the papers in the collection relate to C.A.U.S.E. and its corresponding programs, but there are documents that relate to other programs that she was involved with during her life. The work papers in the collection are made up of photos, newspaper articles and general press, meeting minutes, proposals, evaluations, and correspondence with principals or directors of certain schools and programs. The personal papers include personal correspondence, drawings, resumes and vitaes, and papers corresponding to specific individuals. The correspondence for the programs generally concerns how the program is fairing or requesting certain aid or resources. The personal correspondence ranges from the familial to more business oriented topics.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arraged in 5 series. Each folder either corresponds to a specific program, year range, individual, or type of paper (for the personal papers). For those programs that are contained in multiple folders--including C.A.U.S.E., M.E.S.S., and High School Humanities--the folders are arranged so as to relate to a specific topic within the program. The folders are either arranged alphabetically by last name or program title or chronologically as in the series of newspaper articles and press.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Rosenbaum, Marjorie Rice.; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Ephemera; College-school cooperation.; Education, secondary--United States.; Musical theater--United States.; Choral music.; Middletown (Conn.)--Education--20th century.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Educational Studies Program.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Curricula.
Related Material
Joseph S. Daltry Papers, 1934-1961, Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: C.A.U.S.E. and its programs 1967-2012
  Includes meeting minutes and memos, correspondence, joint proposals, press, and grants.
  - C.A.U.S.E.--general materials, 1980, 1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - C.A.U.S.E.--meeting memos and notes, September 1969-March 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - C.A.U.S.E.--meeting memos and notes, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C.A.U.S.E.--meeting memos and notes, 1980-1986, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - C.A.U.S.E.--grants, 1972-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - C.A.U.S.E.--university and school programs (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - C.A.U.S.E.--joint proposals, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - ESP and C.A.U.S.E. (Project Seed, etc.), 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - C.A.U.S.E.--M.E.S.S. Enrichment Summer School evaluations, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - M.E.S.S. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - M.E.S.S., 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - M.E.S.S.--reports, 1970, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - M.E.S.S.--flyers, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Mount Hermon Summer School, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - American culture seminar--Xavier High School, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Xavier High School Honor Society induction, May 16, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - High School Humanities program--press, 1972-2012 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - High School Humanities program (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hallie, Phillip P.-- High School Humanities "In the Beginning," 1972, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Silent Sounds, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - C.A.U.S.E.--art show, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Human Nature Project, 1970-1971, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hubbard School Breakfast Program, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series II: Other programs and associations 1969-2008
  Includes brochures, press, publications, and memos about specific programs.
  - Wesleyan University documents, 1970-1974, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Wesleyan Reunion & Commencement Weekend, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Wesleyan Volunteers, 1970, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Wesleyan--Vinal Regional Tech, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - New England Association of Schools and Colleges award to Wesleyan, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Adult education, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - ARC--Alternate Route to Certification, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - African-American institute, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Graduate Liberal Studies Program (GLSP), May 24, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hamilton College Convocation, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Middletown Commission on the Arts and Cultural Activities, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Middletown-area teacher paper, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Middletown High School general correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Middletown Public Schools, 1969, 1977, 1983, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Middletown Public School--"Wesleyan and Middletown Schools: A History of Cooperation," 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Music sheets, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - PIMMS, fall 2005 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pilot dance program, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rotary, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - School-Within-A-School program, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - TEP (Teacher Education Program), 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Teacher enrichment, 1971-1972, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Vinal Courses--alternatives, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - '20s seminar, 1972, 1981, 2006, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series III: Important and related individuals 1952-1982
  Includes papers relating to specific individuals. Documents include essays, memos, and correspondence.
  - Campbell, Colin G., 1973, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Daltry, Joseph S., 1952-1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Connecticut Light & Power--Mr. Wallace, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Gehman, Betsy, 1969, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Etherington, Edwin D., 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hallie, Philip, January 21, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Higgins, Paul, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Odets, Watt, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Ruckel, Gilbert C. (Daltry Memorial Room), April 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Shedd, Mark R., 1975, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Snow, Wilbert, May 12, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Series IV: Personal papers 1968-2012
  Includes personal papers of Marjorie Daltry Rosenbaum. Documents include drawings, correspondence, essays, and biographical information.
  - "The Craft of Teaching"--M.D. Rosenbaum, fall 1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Marjorie Daltry--teaching evaluation, September 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Marjorie Daltry Rosenbaum--vitae, 1971, 1973, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Marjorie Daltry Rosenbaum--resume, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Marjorie Rice Daltry (Rosenbaum)--nominations, 1972, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Marjorie Daltry Rosenbaum sabbatical--spring 1978, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Marjorie Rice Daltry--resignation apology, 1971, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Christmas letter--1993, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Marjorie Daltry Rosenbaum--correspondence, 1968-2009 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Marjorie Daltry Rosenbaum--personal papers (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Booklets, 1970, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous papers--programs (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous papers--writings (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Series V: Newspaper clippings and press 1968-2012
  Includes newspaper articles and general press clippings relating to C.A.U.S.E. and its programs or related individuals.
  - C.A.U.S.E. I, 1969-1985 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - News clippings & press I, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - News clippings & press II, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - News clippings & press III, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - News clippings & press IV, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - News clippings & press V, 1973-2012 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - News clippings & press VI, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Oversized press, March 2006 (Box 6)
- Series VI: Photos 1960s-2000s
  Includes both original photos and photocopies of individuals, programs, performances, and art photos. Some photos found in two oversized boxes (6 & 7).
  - Photos--M.E.S.S., 1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photocopies of photos in oversized boxes, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Photos of Marjorie Daltry Rosenbaum, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photos--Wesleyan University E.S.P., undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Photo and photocopies of man, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Photos--lecture, Wesleyan University, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Photos--performance in World Music Hall, CFA, Wesleyan University, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous photos, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Oversized photos of M.E.S.S. Faculty, undated (Box 6)
  - Oversized art photos, undated (Box 7)